Lesson 22 Knowledge and progress
知识和进步
First listen and then answer the following question.
听录音,回答以下问题.
In what two areas have people made no 'progress' at all?
在哪两个方面,人类根本没有取得进步?
loom: v.  赫然耸起
Why does the idea of progress loom so large in the modern world?
为什么进步这个概念在现代世界显得如此突出?
Surely because progress of a particular kind is actually taking place around us
无疑是因为有一种特殊的进步实际上正在我们周围发生,
and is becoming more and more manifest.
而且变得越来越明显.
morality: n.  道德
Although mankind has undergone no general improvement in intelligence or morality,
虽然人类在智力和道德上没有得到普遍提高,
it has made extraordinary progress in the accumulation of knowledge.
但在知识积累方面却取得了巨大的进步.
Knowledge began to increase as soon as the thoughts of one individual
知识的积累从一个人的思想
communicate: v.  交流，交际
could be communicated to another by means of speech.
能通过语言的方式传达给另一个人的那一刻就开始了.
With the invention of writing,a great advance was made,
随着书写的发明,又迈进了一大步,aa
communicate: v.  交流，交际
for knowledge could then be not only communicated but also stored.
因为这样一来,知识不仅能交流,而且能储存了.
Libraries made education possible,and education in its turn added to libraries:
藏书使教育成为可能,而教育反过来又丰富了藏书,
the growth of knowledge followed a kind of compound interest law,
因为知识的增长遵循着一种"滚雪球"的规律.
enhance: v.  增进
which was greatly enhanced by the invention of printing.
印刷术的发明又大大提高了知识增长的速度.
All this was comparatively slow until,with the coming of science,
所有这些发展都比较缓慢而随着科学的到来,
tempo: n.  速率
the tempo was suddenly raised.
增长的速度才突然加快.
Then knowledge began to be accumulated according to a systematic plan.
于是,知识便开始有系统有计划地积累起来.
trickle: n.  涓涓细流, torrent: n.  滔滔洪流
The trickle became a stream:the stream has now become a torrent.
涓涓细流汇成了小溪,小溪现已变成了奔腾的江河.
Moreover,as soon as new knowledge is acquired,it is now turned to practical account.
而且,新知识一旦获得,便得到实际应用.
What is called 'modern civilization'
所谓"现代文明"
is not the result of a balanced development of all man's nature,
并不是人的天性平衡发展的结果,
but of accumulated knowledge applied to practical life.
而是积累起来的知识应用到实际生活中的结果.
humanity: n.  人类
The problem now facing humanity is:
现在人类面临的问题是:
What is going to be done with all this knowledge?
用这些知识去做什么?
As is so often pointed out,knowledge is a two-edged weapon
正像人们常常指出的,知识是一把双刃刀,
which can be used equally for good or evil.
可以用于造福,也可用来为害.
It is now being used indifferently for both.
人们现在正漫不经心地把知识用于这两个方面,
Could any spectacle, for instance,be more grimly whimsical
例如:还有什么情景比以下这些更可怕,更怪诞--
shatter: v.  毁坏
than that of gunners using science to shatter men's bodies
炮兵利用科学毁坏人体、
while,close at hand, surgeons use it to restore them?
而外科医生就在附近用科学抢救被炮兵毁坏的人体.
We have to ask ourselves very seriously
我们不得不严肃地问问我们自己:
what will happen if this twofold use of knowledge,
如果继续利用它的这种双重性,
with its ever-increasing power,continues.
随着知识力量的日益增长将会发生什么情况?